Uma, welcome to the Zero Knowledge
Podcast. Thanks for having me. Awesome.
You want to introduce yourself briefly?
>> Yeah, so I'm co-founder CEO of Syscoin.
Syscoin is a applied cryptography
company.
We probably best known for making the
fastest zero-knowledge virtual machine,
ZKVM for short, in the world known as
SP1.
For those of you who are who aren't
aware,
ZK is this really powerful cryptography
technique where it lets you prove to
someone else something is true without
revealing all the details.
Kind of the canonical real-world example
is that if I can prove to you that, you
know, I'm over 21 without revealing my
birthday or my home address or anything
like that. So, instead of showing a
driver's license at a bar, you can just
show them a proof of, you know, that
you're of age.
We built this ZKVM which um
How can I describe it? I would say it's
somewhat like a foundation model for
cryptography. So, if you want to prove
really complex statements in ZK such as
a roll-up state transition function or
like very complex predicates,
the thing we built makes it super easy.
You just write normal code, you stick it
into SP1, and out comes a proof.
And then yeah, we made it super fast and
really easy to use, which is awesome.
And I would say right now Syscoin,
although historically our ZKVM has been
used mostly for proving blockchains and
proving proving roll-up state transition
functions and things like this in like
Ethereum and other chains, right now
we're really excited about the potential
of cryptography to solve a lot of the
problems that AI poses. I think Balaji
has been an extensive tweeter about this
topic for many years. You're very ahead
of your time, honestly. Thank you. And
so yeah, I think honestly, that's
probably one of the most important
things cryptography can do right now.
And there's like a finally a clear
catalyst. Every model released where the
image stuff or video stuff gets better
and better, it's like we need
cryptography as a defense. So, I think
it's time for cryptography to be on like
a societal stage right now is like a
solution to all the AI stuff.
So I'm very excited about that. Awesome.
So yeah, I actually
actually many years ago,
partly actually because of AI, but also
with social media when people are
talking about misinformation,
disinformation, and so on and so forth.
Years ago, I remember I tweeted
something and I was like, "Oh, so you
want to ban lies on the internet? Okay,
give me a function that says whether the
Riemann hypothesis is true."
>> [laughter]
>> Right? And so you know, that's a
reductio ad absurdum where we we don't
know whether it's true and it could be
true and it's plausible that it's true,
but there's many things in math which
have really arcane counterexamples that,
you know, you get up to n equals
whatever and it it's actually not true.
Um
and uh
so but as I thought about that, I was
like, "Well, how would you code
truegle?"
t r u g l e, you know, if you were
actually, you know, going to do it,
right? How would you do it? And the
thing is LLMs get you some of the way
towards that, right? Because they will
take a statement and they'll do at least
a probabilistic search of the literature
and pull things up and so on and so
forth.
Right? And the thing is though, of
course, then those assertions themselves
need to be underpinned with citations.
And then that's how you get to on-chain
everything.
And so my view is like
with LLMs, actually you can you can kind
of show a version of this today. If you
ask any
LLM to summarize some major crypto hack,
it will show you probably some link that
shows some on-chain block explorer
record, among other things.
And so that's currently only used to
document financial things,
like the on-chain transaction, you know,
during let's say FTX had a hack or
whatever during that period.
Right? But as more and more things get
logged on chain then more and more
references from LLM's will point to on
chain events and we get what I call the
ledger of record and I think the same
could be maybe a big part of that. So
you had some slides so maybe you want to
go through your slides? Oh yeah. What's
your background by the way? You're born
in the US you
um
What's your
>> Yeah born in the US. Um yeah I was born
in the US. I went to school at MIT. Was
a double major in math and CS. I've
always really loved so that's kind of
how I got into ZK.
Um
and yeah I mean ZK and cryptography have
a lot of fascinating math and that was
really like the draw for me um
and actually before ZK I was doing some
AI stuff so I was like at Google brain
doing research into like early LLM's and
this is pre-GPT. I was doing some stuff
with BERT back then. Uh so I'm familiar
with that world and now it's like
exciting to see the synthesis. This yes.
I mean you know the thing is
I you know I was actually also in
machine learning prior to the deep
learning era but from the standpoint of
genomics and diagnostics and and
whatnot. And you know just to digress on
that for a second before we get into ZK
stuff like you know all the stuff with
hidden Markov models and conditional
random fields and you know
um
it was surprising to me that
transformers worked as well as they did
to get long range context in there. It's
even more surprising to me that
diffusion models work.
And and yet they do.
That you know you wouldn't necessarily
intuit from the equations that they
would work as well as they do in
practice. I don't know if you have any
thoughts on that. Maybe we talk about
that and then go to the next. I mean
when you were working on BERT did you
think I obviously there was there were
people who had the graphs of scaling and
here's how it's going to go. Right? So
there was some intuition that it could
maybe get there, but
but it but it worked a lot I mean, the
jump between GPT-2 and GPT-3 and then
chat GPT in terms of usability was
very non-linear, I think from you know,
right? Go ahead. Maybe Were you
surprised by that? Oh, I mean,
absolutely.
Uh I think even the close people closest
to the metal on this stuff seemed
surprised at like how well it's going
and even today like the level of math
problems they're solving and stuff like
that. Um
Yeah, I I would say I I was very
surprised that
this process which, you know, with deep
learning there aren't really that many
proofs. Like in cryptography, everything
we do is proven. Like it's
deterministic.
You have very concrete bounds and proofs
for everything.
Um
Yeah, and LLMs is just
it's like why does deep learning work?
Kind of vibes-based. Um but right now
the vibes are really good. It works
really well. Right. And I think it's
funny because Well, actually go through
your talk and then let's talk. Go. Prove
what's real. Okay, cool. Um
So, yeah, I mean, I think you One of
your favorite quotes um
is AI makes everything fake, crypto
makes it real again. Yes.
>> Um
And yeah, I think like the problem is
very clear now. AI makes everything fake
and we're seeing that every single day.
So, it's like whether it's this DoorDash
driver, you know, kind of faking the
delivery. Maybe that's a little bit of a
trivial example that went quite viral on
X. To something like, oh, is Jeffrey
Epstein still alive? Or it's like the
White House posting digitally altered
pictures. Or it's politicians getting
deep faked. Um or you know, celebrities
getting deep faked doing all sorts of
things. Like The problem is I think
today is like extremely clear.
And it's only getting to be worse and
worse as these models get better and
better.
Uh so, like the seed dance released
recently of like the really good video
models that like, you know, can
really impersonate any celebrity or any
person like is very clear that AI makes
everything fake is kind of like a huge
problem for the internet. So,
yeah, that's like the problem statement.
Mhm.
Um, and then I think like one really
interesting thing So, people have
identified this problem statement. It's
not, you know, that hard to understand
why it's so problematic. Um, I would say
the state of the art right now for
trying to detect AI is use AI.
So, people have like trained these AI
detectors uh, to train models to say,
"Hey, is something real or is like
something from the model?" And recently
it's a think we did this, you know,
benchmarking study to,
you know, evaluate those claims and say,
"Hey, does AI detection actually work?"
And we published, you know, this data
set
of realistic AI images and um,
tried to benchmark all the leading
commercial detectors.
And uh, you can actually go to the
website aidetect.synthesis.xyz.
But the resounding answer was like,
"Yeah, the AI detection stuff is not
robust and it just does not work." Um,
I'm going to slightly argue with you on
this maybe, which is to say on text as
opposed to images, right? Um,
so much So, this reminds me a little bit
of uh, I'm not I'm not really arguing
with the results of your paper, but on
the macro thing, right? And and it's so,
um,
with Snapchat,
you know, it has a deterrent to someone
taking a screenshot of, you know, like
like a disappearing message. Now, of
course, you or I or someone who's a
computer scientist will say, "Well,
there's still the analog hole. You can
just hold up another phone and record
it." And you know, if you want to, you
can just take a a phone and record it
and that doesn't have, the you know, you
can defeat it with a sufficiently
motivated attacker relatively easily,
right? However, most people aren't that
motivated, and so the simple and dumb
screenshot detection thing sets the norm
and makes it relatively hard to do
screenshots, right? Similar to how, you
know, you could people could work around
the Twitter 140 character limit by
pasting in screenshots of 140 you know,
more than 140 characters, but they
didn't for a long time, right? And my
view is that there's a lot of AI text on
X, for example, that at least I can
trivially detect. It's not this, it's
that, and the M dashes, and and so on
and so forth, right? And there's certain
people who just are clearly AI posters
because of just the style. It's like
this over dramatic kind of style. It's
It jumps out to you immediately when you
see it because you see it a lot. It's
like seeing the same person writing over
and over, you know? And pangram.com or
something like that feels pretty good at
detecting ChatGPT type slop, which you
see a lot of. And Claude and ChatGPT,
for whatever reason, have very similar
text voice, I think, right? On this kind
of thing.
Yeah, I mean, I guess they're trained on
the same data to a certain extent.
>> Yes. Whereas
images, you know, maybe uh
I I guess it depends on the class of
image.
I mean, obviously with hands and things
like that, gymnasts, they're finally
starting to get good with gymnastics
with uh with C dance because those are
unusual poses, but they do like physics
simulations, I guess, to to train them.
I don't know, maybe you have a thought
on that. You you understand my point,
right? Like, AI detection may not work
100% of the time, but for text, I think
it currently works well enough
to get a lot of the ChatGPT type slop at
a fairly high Like, you can certainly
see it visually.
You know, like a human can see it, then
it then if if if it's unsubtle enough
for us to see, let me pause there. Yeah,
I
I do agree that the text stuff, at least
right now there are these what
watermarks almost like the M-dash or the
patterns you were saying like oh it's X
this is X not Y. Right. Um
but I I still think that
similar to images actually like the
study we did basically was you take an
image that an AI generates and by the
way these things are pretty good. Like I
actually I have gotten personally fooled
a bunch of times.
>> Yes. Yes. Sure.
>> so empirically it seems to be really
good and then we did the study where you
basically perturb the image a bit so you
blur it or you crop it or you add some
like in indiscernible Gaussian noise to
the image and then the AI detectors all
completely break. And I think even in
text that's kind of true right and
I mean who's to say using AI to help you
write some of your tweets maybe that's
not even a bad thing necessarily right?
Like ultimately like content is content
and maybe you're saying something
interesting with the AI's help but like
a lot of people do these tricks where
they're like get the output from ChatGPT
and then they tell ChatGPT remove all
the M-dashes and then
then it's not detectable.
>> No that's true. I I guess the thing is
so here's my view on that. It's my
emerging view so at least here's our
current standard on this. We so at NS
our our rule is no public undisclosed
AI.
Mhm. Right? So why do I say that? Well
first is people can just go full AI and
full AI means
like cuz AI is a shortcut.
Yeah. And as a shortcut
it's a I think it's a good term because
people can take too many shortcuts and
they fake it and they don't know what
they're doing and so on. The more expert
you are the more legitimate it is to
take a shortcut cuz you know how to do
it the normal way right? Um
and it's like writing down a theorem
without doing the full proof every time.
It's right using a function call right?
There's a reason that people use
shortcuts. Okay but they can overuse
them, fine.
So, the alternative is no AI, which is a
lot of people actually are going to go
to, and there's like an anti-AI
movement, fine. But no public
undisclosed AI, I think in four words it
captures So, you can use private AI
and that's undisclosed cuz you're going
and editing your own stuff, right?
I mean you're you're or like you're
editing code, who cares, you know, using
it for yourself, right?
Public disclosed AI, when whether it's a
watermark at the bottom right or it's
like an animation, a comic, a movie,
something like that, no one can get mad
cuz you're not trying to pull one over
on on somebody, right?
It's public undisclosed AI that gets
people mad and at least if I analyze my
own reaction on that
I don't when someone is sending me
something that's obviously AI
I think they're either stupid or lazy.
They're
Why it they're stupid because they can't
see the
obvious AI tells. Like they send an AI
slop slide deck or they have a AI
webpage that has a lot of um like it's
one thing if they say, "Hey, this is a
prototype, check it out." Okay, fine,
right? But that's disclosed AI.
If it's undisclosed and it's just got
like a wall of AI cuz AI tends to you
know, in AI images, they're more full of
people than normal images by default,
you know, if you've noticed unless you
actually pull that back, right? Like
the the their outdoor scenes have too
many people often, right? Um
and that's like one tell, right? Uh
and similarly AI pages and AI slide
decks are not succinct.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
They're just really right? And so,
either they're dumb and they can't tell
what's good or they're lazy and they're
hitting a few keys and then sending me a
bunch of slop and I have to go through
it and fundamentally they're taxing the
other side. It's like someone leaving a
voicemail memo for you.
Yeah. You know? Like I have to verify
everything cuz they didn't verify
everything. And so when they whenever I
get an AI message from somebody,
I downweight them
because of that.
Mhm. And I and I downweight them as a
poster and so on and so forth because
they they just
they're taking shortcuts in a way that
makes me question their judgment.
Now, if it gets good enough that Go
ahead. Say what you were going to say.
Well, I think one reason that fake
images and fake text is a little
different is I mean, historically, you
could just write whatever words you
want. It even pre-AI, you could just
write a bunch of things that were not
true. Like you could lie. So I think
humans are very used to critically
evaluating the text they see because
like
people can always just write whatever.
Um I think we're much less used to being
able to critically evaluate images we
see cuz historically,
it was pretty hard. I mean, okay, you
had things like Photoshop and this and
that, but like, you know, it'd be pretty
hard to
really fake something elaborate or like
fake, for example, the president of the
United States doing like a 1-minute long
video saying whatever. Uh
you just could not have done that in the
past. And now with the AI tools, it's
very easy to do that. So so it's really
interesting you say that. And and I want
continue your presentation. My I agree
and I'll give a partial counterargument,
which is I actually think most of the
images and videos people have seen are
television or movies
Mhm. until recently.
And uh those were actually all fictional
and synthetic.
And so they kind of live within a world
where some significant fraction of their
inbound training data Mhm. is fictional,
as seen by the extent to which people
reference
I don't know, Star Wars or The
Handmaid's Tale or something like that.
Like the you know, Harry Potter. That's
actually more real for many people than
actual history.
>> [laughter]
>> But that's like disclosed.
It is disclosed, but I don't think they
can actually
Go ahead. Say say say say. Oh, yeah. I
was just going to say that it's
disclosed and that you know it's not you
know it's made up.
I I think you and I know it's made up.
But I but I think Okay, here's my
argument on this and let's continue, but
the
I call it Jurassic ballpark.
Mhm. Like you know, Jurassic Park has
the scene where uh see I'm actually
referencing a fictional movie scene to
explain fictional movie scenes. It's
very meta, okay? So, Jurassic Park has
the scene where the dinosaurs have
amphibian DNA spliced in because
the scientists didn't know what to make
of that part, so they spliced in
amphibian DNA. And that leads to you
know, the the dinosaurs reproducing. The
point being that when we
are dealing with a situation that we
don't have personal experience of.
Like we don't have personal data on. You
implicitly rely on some movie you've
seen about that area to tell you how
it's like.
For example, unless you've actually
been if unless you've worked at CIA
or you know people at Palantir, you
don't really understand
what the actual CIA is as opposed to the
movie version. You think the movie
version is in the ballpark and even if
it's like more dramatized or whatever,
right?
And and it's often just totally not.
And so that's why I mean like you're
right that we kind of know it's
fictional, but we don't know what
reality is. And so often we think that
the fictional is just a jazzed up
version of the real as opposed to like
totally totally totally off.
Mhm. So, anyway, so the reason
the reason I say that is I think there's
a huge opportunity. One of the things I
want to fund at some point is people
taking actual history and then using AI
to dramatize it.
Mhm. So, now it's actually more
fictional it's fictional but factual.
Fictional depiction of real events, you
know? Anyway, could keep going. I didn't
mean to digress. Keep going. There's all
these examples and like it's actually
pretty fascinating. So, I'm sensing the
receipts.
Yeah, I mean even I mean this is like
kind of maybe a mundane example, but we
did all these what we had a bunch of
different categories of like real cases
where AI deep fakes could be somewhat
harmful. And one is just, you know,
receipts and like reimbursements. And we
had AI generate a bunch of images that
were like taking a real receipt and
modifying the numbers to be much greater
than they actually were like at by an
order of magnitude. And then we put them
through these AI image detectors.
And
it it's turns out like, you know,
they're okay. They're like, "Oh, this is
a 36% chance it's AI. This is a 44%
chance it's AI. Maybe look at the
original."
>> Something.
Uh
These are actually real photos. No, I
mean but did what did the original come
up as 0%? Oh, um I don't have those
numbers here, but I think it was like
pretty accurate. Um so,
>> Well, cuz the reason Yeah, the reason I
ask is it I'd I'd be I'd love to see
that data if you could pull it at some
point because even if the detector
was saying 36% if it could if it had
variance, you could rescale the axis,
you know what I mean? Like if the if the
real photos were left shifted relative
to the fake photos, you could recast it
as, you know, like a binary classifier
problem. Yeah, yeah, like basically the
distribution of real like the
distribution of fake. But then the
problem is if you just do simple
perturbations to the AI generated stuff
like you add a simple blur or noising.
And I mean if you are looking at the
video of this and not the podcast, you
can see these basically look
pretty identical to the human eye. The
AI detector says 4% chance this is AI.
So, it's just not robust.
>> Wow, interesting. Okay. Um and that's
like
>> Okay.
>> That's true across a variety of
examples. And then that's even true
across a variety of problems. So, we did
like some other examples. Okay, this
one's maybe a little more higher stakes.
You take a picture of a car that's not
damaged. You add AI to like add dents
and scratches. Maybe you're doing
insurance fraud.
Again, similar story. The AI says, "Hey,
okay, like the original version when you
just do naive like, hey Grok, tell me
like add dents." Um the AI detector will
say, "Hey, it's like 44% chance." Or
something like that. But when you add
some trivial blurring and noising, the
AI detector goes down to like 2%.
Mhm. Um so,
Okay. There's There's other, you know,
then there then we took pictures of like
real editorial photos. So, you could
imagine like war zones or like, you
know, other journalism or famous
political leaders and like kind of
similar story across all these different
categories of images.
And so, our conclusion from this study
was that AI detection is a dead end.
Um like fundamentally, and I think if
you think about how these models are
trained, it kind of makes sense. Like
when you're training these models,
you're optimizing some sort of loss
function from like the generation to
like the manifold of real data.
And you're literally optimizing so that
the things you spit out look
statistically very similar to the real
data.
And so, it's not that difficult to
imagine that it's going to be very hard
to detect what's real and what's fake
cuz the models are being trained to
minimize that.
Um and there's actually like a bunch of
work, without going into too much
detail, and also I I mean, obviously I'm
no longer an AI researcher, so I'm not
like super in the weeds here, but
there's a bunch of work done at MIT and
by a bunch of other people on
adversarial examples.
Where basically they had these detectors
back then it was these ImageNet
classifiers and then they added they did
a similar study they added like some
simple noise and stuff like that and
then they found that the image
classifiers more robust to these
adversarial perturbations. So you could
always kind of find some perturbation of
an image like you would take an image of
a panda you would add a simple blurring
it would look the same to a human but
then the classifier would flip from
panda to like dog. Right. And this is
this is to do with basically just the
fact that you would never actually see a
point
of that kind in the like the manifold of
where pandas live. You could perturb it
out to the manifold where dogs live
because there was no
training data along that vector
typically. It's like very thin on that
axis. Yeah but
again I I don't like I wasn't in this
research line so my naive like way I
think about it is like just these are
such high dimensional decision
boundaries like we're going to mess up
at some point and like there's going to
be some point in the decision boundary
where you think it's a dog but like to a
human it looks like a panda and like
it's just inevitable cuz like the
decision you're just operating over such
like a high dimensional space that's
kind of how I think about it. Yeah.
There's a there's actually a
like a the pedal width versus length
thing the like there's this iris data
set in um
in R I'll bring this up here.
>> Oh yeah yeah it's a famous yeah I I've
heard of it. The famous one you know
what I'm talking about right? And so
it's like um
like something like this
is uh probably a 3D Actually you know
what a better one is like Swiss roll or
something like that right?
Um
in 3D.
Basically let me see if I can pull this
up.
So something like this so Swiss roll,
right? Is sort of something where
um you have like the yellow category and
the green category, aquamarine, light
yellow, blue, right? And in three space
they're clearly distinct. Um but if and
let's say this was, you know,
uh the panda and this is the dog or
something like that. If you put a vector
and you perturbed it in such a way that
you had a point that was
I don't know, 60% of the way towards
this blue part and there's no normal
points that existed here in image space.
That's my intuition for how the
perturbation works. I should look that
up but that's that's certainly how it
works with low dimensional things and
probably something like that works with
higher dimensional. Um
and you know, similarly to the uh
this uh the pedal [clears throat] went
with one over here.
Anyway, I'm going to I'm going to get
into succinct because this is the
probabilistic. Let's get into your
deterministic. Go, go, go. So, this this
also if you had something over here
that'd be outside of the training set,
you could misclassify it as, you know,
uh uh
as a circle when it was actually a
triangle or vice versa. Okay, go, go,
go. It's all all yours. Yeah, yeah,
we're we uh so we fully established that
yeah, the AI detecting eyes was like not
going to work. Um that seems bad. Um so,
it's succinct. Well, okay. AI makes
everything fake. That's what you said.
What's the what's the solution? Crypto
makes it real again. Yep.
>> So, um
we're big believers of that as succinct
doesn't apply to cryptography company.
So, now like let's dive into what that
actually means. Um so, today like how
does content actually get posted online?
I mean, basically first it gets
captured, whether it's on like a
smartphone or a camera or a microphone
for audio or some other sensor. Then it
goes through some editing,
uh whether it's like Photoshop or these
AI editing tools, and then it gets
published. So, it's like across social
media, news services, news wires,
traditional media, YouTube, and then it
gets consumed. So, you look at the
content and you say like you you just
look at the content. So, that's kind of
like the current life cycle and yeah,
throughout all of this there's like no
verification. So, it would be impossible
for you to tell if something's real or
something's fake.
Now,
how does crypto help with this? Um so,
this is like what we're building at
sense of sync, but um we think there's
this notion of basically what we call
the provable technology stack. So, at
every point in this like capture, edit,
publish, consume life cycle, you insert
in cryptography and provable technology
to prove it's real.
So, to start, um when you capture
something,
>> Yeah, this is exact This is
You must have taken some of my content
and and maybe
>> yeah. Okay, okay. A lot of it is very
inspired by like a lot of your work.
Yeah. Okay. Well, this is great. So,
basically there's a crypto camera and
then chain of custody, ledger of record,
public verification. Exactly This is
exactly the stuff that
I've wanted out there for whether it's
scientific experiments or something. You
can keep going. I'm listening. I I I
know this but say say what you're going
to say. Yeah, yeah. I mean, and yeah,
like all credit where it's due, I think
you identified that this is a solution
maybe like five years ahead of its time,
five years ahead of the problem.
Um like and you're you're always very
ahead of your time. So, a lot of this
stuff is like very inspired by your work
and I I think there's a lot of other
like I think Marc Andreessen has talked
about this actually and I'll get to this
later like the head of Instagram is now
talking about this.
Um but yeah, they Okay, just to get into
what is a provable tech stack. So, at
capture, um
things are captured on hardware devices.
Uh hardware devices can have private
keys that are binded to the device. So,
you have a cryptographic chip with the
key. That's kind of how you can think of
it. And basically like as the raw sensor
data is coming into the camera,
the cryptographic chip signs like the
content of the raw sensor data, and it
binds like the content being captured to
the specific device, time, and location.
So, that's cryptographic capture.
Then, as the content gets edited, um you
have this like chain of custody and
chain of edits. So, there's a
cryptographically signed manifest for
every transformation you do, whether
it's like cropping or color correction
or grading or things like that, and you
basically keep this append-only record
of what's going on to the image.
And then finally, you publish
the piece of content and the manifest of
the original signature when it got
captured to the chain of edits, and you
publish that to a unbiased permanent
ledger, which is like this ledger
record.
And then, when the content actually gets
consumed, so it's like in some front
end, whether it's YouTube or Instagram
or X,
um
the front end integrates with the
ledger,
and it basically verifies all the
signatures, verifies they're real, and
displays that information to the user.
And you know, if the user wants more
information, they can just click and
like verify all the signatures for
themselves. So,
today on most content platforms, we have
the blue check mark for like your
verified identity. You can imagine in
the future maybe all content comes with
the pink check mark that says, "Hey,
this content is like actually real, and
like here's the device, and here's like
the series of transformations that
happened to it."
Mhm. Very cool. So, okay, keep going.
So yeah, this is the provable tech
stack, and this is like all the stuff
we're building at Zsync. Um
and yeah, I I think to your point, um
you talked about this for a really long
time, which is like very cool. And I
think finally, like other people are
starting to catch on cuz like the
problem is finally very evident. So,
there's this um
quote from Adam Mosseri who runs
Instagram.
>> cryptographically sign a capture. Yep.
Yeah, he posted at the at the start of
2026 he posted like, "Hey, here's
Instagram's like kind of what we're
thinking about what I'm thinking about
right now." And he says that
basically we're going to move from
assuming what we see is real by default
to starting with skepticism. So he's
kind of identifying this like AI makes
everything fake problem. And then he
said, "Okay, platforms like Instagram
will do good work identifying AI
content, but they'll get worse at it
over time as AI gets better. It will be
more practical to fingerprint real media
than fake media. And then this is kind
of like the thesis of Prove It's Real
and all this cryptography stuff. Camera
manufacturers will cryptographically
sign images at capture creating a chain
of custody."
So
>> Yes.
Yeah, I mean even like people like Adam
who are running Instagram are saying
that crypto crypto is going cryptography
is going to be the solution to this like
AI the problems that AI
creates for like content platforms.
>> That's right. Now I think actually
crypto social and AI are all interlinked
here because another piece of this,
which is actually implicit in like the
first part of what he's saying, starting
with skepticism, pay attention to who is
sharing something and why.
Um I think [clears throat] actually AI
and crypto together um
are going to result in
you know, like you know, I think the
future is China versus the internet. Did
we talk about that?
Have you heard me say it talk write
about that?
>> I've heard you say a little bit about
it. So I think the future is a
billion-person Chinese superstate or a
thousand million-person network states.
Why? Because everybody thinks about AI
improving productivity, but that was
only true within a tribe where you can
trust you know, you can share
information
>> [clears throat]
>> and what do we call it, indexing or
surveillance, right? Because one is good
and one is consensual and one is bad,
and one is not, right? So, it is
indexing everything and it's learning
everything and it doesn't really miss
like a single remark somewhere. AI can
pull out a remark from like 3 years ago
and surface it and synthesize in a way
that no human you know, or or you'd have
to have a very attentive smart human.
Human It was human limited that level of
surveillance from before, right?
So, or that level of synthesis. You
know, the till to look over over every
commit and find security holes from
years ago. It's amazing, right? But that
operates within the tribe. Outside the
tribe,
it's spam, it's scams, it's slop, right?
And so, basically, the cost of
production goes way down, but the cost
of verification goes way up.
And so, this part about paying attention
to who is sharing something and why,
I think another big piece of this is web
three of trust.
So, you take web of trust like I trust
you because I know you and I've known
you in person. And when you
cryptographically sign something on a
camera, there is the human part of that
as well as the machine part. Like,
ultimately, if I wasn't actually there
with you in the room,
I have to trust at some point some human
assertion that this data because I can
see it on chain that it was stamped at
this time and um there's various proofs
that one can put on there like proof of
location, proof of this, proof of that.
But ultimately,
at like you as a human have to tell me
that you didn't manipulate it before you
cryptographically
signed it. Like, you you cuz you could
do something upstream like the analog
hole upstream, you know, the equivalent
of putting something in front of the
camera, right? Um
and we can make it hard to do that. We
can't make it impossible to do that. And
uh unless like every single camera has
one of these and I think maybe it'll get
there eventually,
but there'll also be a demand for those
things that don't have these, kind of
like burner phones, you know what I
mean, right?
And so and and there's so many phones
out there, there's billions of phones
that do not have crypto chips in them
that you, you know,
like just like you can get on a little
laptop, you could get a fakeable phone,
you know, right? And people will also
revolt against
too much tracking or what have you, you
know, they want it to be free, whatever.
Anyway, I think that's another piece of
this is
the full supply chain of custody
includes the person who's sending it to
you. And so who is sharing something and
why? If they're within your crypto
tribe,
crypto thinks tribally natively, and AI
is going to make people think tribally
necessarily.
Mhm.
And so everything reduces to digital
tribes, where digital borders and
physical borders become the same. And
China is the biggest digital tribe of
all,
because they can centrally moderate all
of their chat apps and so on and so
forth. Like they just whatever AI
detection stuff they roll out in WeChat,
they can force human verification and so
on. And so you have just a central choke
point where basically a billion people
get on boarded into
whatever AI detection, prevention, fake
detection things they want. But the rest
of the world doesn't have the same level
of I mean, Google and others can roll
out certain levels of things, but
they've almost opted for a more anarchic
standard because of the whole freedom of
speech fight, right? Which I get, but
there's a there's a under correction and
an over correction on anything, and what
you want is consensual moderation, I
think. Anyway, so it's a complement to
what you're saying. Keep going. Um yeah,
I I think what you're
I think in the future like it's not I
don't imagine a future where every photo
posted on Instagram is required that
it's real, cuz like I mean, some AI
pictures are really cool or like really
interesting.
>> Sure. I think it's more like to your
point about
>> Disclosure. consensual moderation, it's
like Yes.
>> want to prove something's real, and I
think a lot of people deeply care about
that, well then now you finally using
cryptography actually have the tools to
do that. Um
and then
yeah, if you want to any if you want to
follow content creators that have those
capabilities or only post real stuff,
you can do that. And then, you know,
social media is one thing, but obviously
for things like journalism, I think uh
Nikita Bier, who's the head of product
at X, tweeted about this. There's these
accounts posting totally fake pictures
from the Iranian war and it it's like
pretty bad and like misinformed and so
obviously that's like not okay. Um and I
think this sort of technology
>> Right. I I'm hopeful will help with
much higher stakes situations like that
or you know, political ads or like what
the president is saying or things like
that. I think will be really important
to like prove what's real there.
Great. Okay, cool. All right, keep
going.
Cool. I mean, yeah, I think the rest of
the slides are just like a little more
detail about what's going on. Um so
already today you said, you know, how
many cameras actually have this
cryptographic chip? Well, fun fact,
every single iPhone does have a secure
enclave that has this capability. Um and
so, you know, interacting with these
enclaves across all the device types is
really hard and so we've built this SDK
to kind of provide a unified experience
for people who want to use it.
>> How or how's how's it cost? How much
does it cost? Or is it The Yeah, yeah,
the SDK's Well, it's not published yet,
but we're going to publish it. Okay, I
want to try I I will commission some
apps on this once you publish this.
Okay, yeah, yeah, that'll be cool. That
That is actually the foundation of a new
kind of media.
Yes. Yeah, yeah, I yes. Yeah, I think
there's a lot of potential there. I
think
uh
incentivizing decentralized media
collection in an AI-first, crypto-first,
social-first, mobile-first,
internet-first way,
this is like a missing piece of that.
Mhm. Where we have all of these quote
reporters from around the world
and on any topic that we care about we
can incentivize first party reporting
where we pay in crypto and we verify in
crypto where we pay in cryptocurrency
and verify with cryptography. We
essentially have like a decentralized
news outlet.
So this is something that I want to get
going and maybe we can collaborate on
this. We can talk about this right after
this. Yeah, that would be very cool.
Um
and
yeah, but citizen journalism like you
kind of well, especially now with the AI
generation stuff, you actually do need a
way to verify that it's actually real
and so I I totally agree with this. And
I think we would focus it on
the news of the network state and
startup societies and cryptocurrency and
technology, biotech, areas that I think
are not well covered but should be
because they are for
tech decision makers.
So because you thing is news is a huge
topic, right? And rather than the news
of the state, we focus on the news of
the network.
And those types of things that are
like with a relatively small amount of
money, you could get much more coverage
of them because they're more important
for technical decision makers.
And that's kind of the niche that
all of these tech outlets basically
abdicated
and actually in part the reason they
abdicated is because a full-time
journalist
is uh like a professional journalist
is often somebody who doesn't actually
know technology because if they did,
they wouldn't be a full-time journalist,
they'd be actually like a player on the
field, right? Building.
So moreover, by being a quote full-time
journalist, they're loyal to the
journalist tribe as opposed to
technologies tribe and technologies
tribe is taking away revenue from
journalist tribe. So a lot of their
coverage is very hostile.
So the way we solve both of those
problems in my view is rather than one
full-time journalist making, I don't
know, 50k or whatever it is. We have 50
part-time journalists who earn $1,000
bounties
for writing up what they know. Mhm. And
because they have domain knowledge, if
they write up one article a year, we're
good.
Right.
So, that's like NS news.
And so, maybe we can integrate
>> Yeah, yeah. Yeah, we Okay, yeah, we
should talk about that. Yeah, you you
can build that with our stuff now. It's
like pretty The whole point of this is
it makes it easy. Okay, great. Go go
Keep going and let's talk more. Go.
Cool. Um yeah, then there's the probable
edit history part where after you get
the probable capture, you do all the
stuff you want to do with it. Um and
there is actually these existing
standards for it called C2PA, which kind
of tracks which is a metadata standard
that kind of tracks, okay, who
what series of edits did you do, what
production did you do, and then it
appends it to a manifest. And then
finally, after you've kind of compiled
the proof of capture, the proof of
edits, um it gets published to this
thing, which you came up with this name,
the ledger of record,
which
uh is this like open unbiased,
you know,
place where all this content gets
published, and then that's where all the
content that gets displayed in front
ends. So, for example, Instagram or X or
whatever, it can read from this ledger,
which is basically just a database
um of like what is actually real or not.
Um
So,
that's kind of our vision for probable
technologies and like the whole stack.
Um and yeah, we kind of imagine that
this stuff will show up one day in every
single app every single real picture on
the internet will have a pink checkmark
that says
it's real with all the signatures and
all the cryptographic proof, and you can
anyone viewing a picture can just look
at that and know what's actually real.
So, that's our kind of vision for how
cryptography is going to solve a lot of
the problems posed by AI. Amazing.
Okay. So,
um
which she people should go to
succinct.xyz? Yeah, people can go to
succinct.xyz
um or follow us on Twitter @succinctlabs
and we will be posting We're building
this whole stack and we're going to be
releasing like a lot of products and um
related technologies um you know, in the
in the coming months. Okay, awesome.
Okay. So, It would be interesting to
hear kind of your vision for how you
think this is going to like
be put into the world or like
Yeah,
you've been talking about these ideas
for so long. I'm just curious to know
like more about why it got What got you
excited about it and like how you think
this is going to like proliferate. Sure.
So,
um
well, what got me excited about this? Um
you know, in the '90s, like, you know,
when I was I was a kid then. So, I'm
about maybe 10 15 years older than you,
something like that. Or I I I mean, I
don't I I would never ever presume to
know your age or whatever. Just saying
like probably probably in that ballpark,
right? In the '90s, um
nobody cared about politics.
It was something where it was literally
being interested in politics was like
being interested in
the train tables or the bus schedule or
something like that, you know? And it
was genuinely something Why would you
care about this legislative this and
that? No one cares. And you cared about
music, movies, sports, video games,
whatever, right? It was just a vacation
from history.
And so, like, for much of my life, I
was essentially just an apolitical
academic and uh all I cared about was
math, computer science, bioinformatics,
all that kind of stuff.
And then,
um
after uh you know, essentially the full
political breakdown of arguably, you can
you can argue when it started, 2001,
2008, 2015, 2020. Everyone's got a
different moment, right? Um
the you know, there's a saying uh which
I is amazing tweet, if the news is fake,
imagine history.
Mhm. Okay. And you actually start, you
know, realizing a lot of the movies in
the '90s
were almost like the collective
unconscious was putting out movies like
The Matrix,
um Eternal Sunshine of the Spotless
Mind, The Game, Dark City,
um
Fight Club, 12 Monkeys, all of which
were essentially about your, you know,
Memento, right? Your memory playing
tricks on you.
Mhm.
>> And in some sense, the world was not
what it seemed, right? The Truman Show,
right? The Truman Show, The Matrix, all
of these are like you're living in a
constructed world, right? Memento, your
memory of the past isn't the same,
right? And
it was as if like almost the collective
world was waking up to realize that the
centralized century of the 20th century
was an illusion in some ways, and that
there's more to the past and they they'd
sort of been, you know, hypnotized,
zombified, or what have you.
And so, putting those together,
you know, I I started asking questions
like, how do we actually know what's
really true? Like, let me give an
example. Uh maybe a seemingly trivial
example, but this is in the network
state book. Let's even take F equals MA.
Mhm. How would how would you actually
know that's true? If you track it all
the way back,
ultimately, there are scatter plots.
Uh you know, when people rolling balls
down inclined planes, right? Where they
are taking X and Ys and correlating them
and then effectively doing a line fit.
That is then generalized into this
deterministic physical law, right?
Underpinning everything that we think is
true is ultimately a set of observations
that you could track all the way back to
Newton. Like it you know, the famous you
know, apocryphal apple falling down,
right? Like what you think you know is
true, if you can track back all the
citations all the way back to root,
that's the reason that we think it's
true. Why is that actually sometimes
important to do? Well, uh
I'm forgetting this is a whole
complicated story and I I think it's
something like
there's a the story about vitamin C, I
believe in medicine. I'm probably
getting this wrong and I'll look it up,
but it's it's like vitamin C
supplementation,
but
it's uh
what was it? Spinach? There was like a
there's a whole medical story
um
Hold on, let me find this. The iron
myth, right? Spinach is a good source of
iron, right? And
this is one of those things where
somebody tried to track it back
and it was
um it it was either this or something
else where when you tried to track the
citations all the way back,
it was a complicated mixture of
multiple mistaken citations on top of
each [clears throat] other. Uh I think
this is it.
Here.
Let's look at this.
The sudden thing, I think this is it.
Um basically
the complex and convoluted messes of one
call for want of a less complex name,
the iron decimal point error myth and
essentially
it is
uh
decimal error knowledge gap.
It's like It's like a myth piled on top
of a myth. It's like something
complicated enough that I have to go and
remember it, right? You can look at this
this document. The point being that
that is a concrete example of something
where someone literally dug through
every citation going all the way back
and they found that the thing that
people thought was solid was actually
based on nothing, right? All kinds of
social science has failed the
reproducibility crisis in this way,
right? So, all kinds of political
science
history
social science
is something where now with LLMs
we can
back solve and go all the way back,
right? Because it's it's much better
search, right? So, you can track it all
the way back to all the original
citations behind a claim,
right? You can push it pretty hard to
that deep research, whatever you want to
call it. Like uh you know, the team of
agents saying the broadcast can pull
like a thousand sources or something
like that, much faster than a human can.
And so, now we can really remember that
Truegole thing that I was talking about.
Yeah. We can really start interrogating.
It's almost like the um
you know, the Bertrand Russell program
in math of really trying to put math on
an axiomatic basis,
right? And really trying to have as few
axioms as possible build the whole thing
from set theory and and I think it's
like on page 347 he says, "And thus we
prove that 1 + 1 = 2." Yeah, yeah.
You know the thing I'm talking about,
right? Yeah, yeah.
>> It's like It's like a famous thing in
math, right? So, you're probably aware
of it. So,
so like that
I
I wanted to I realized how
ignorant I was
about what had actually happened in the
past, about what scientific facts were
actually true, about how scoped my
knowledge was, and I started to ask what
I know this is a longer answer than you
wanted, but this is what led me to this,
right? It's like uh it's like you know,
as a research scientist, and you're a
research scientist also,
we're in the unusual position of being
pre-headline people.
What I mean by that is like this is more
true on the Twitter of like 5 years ago,
but there's a fair number of let's call
them normie NPC type people
who
genuinely cannot believe something is
true until it's appeared in a headline.
Mhm. That is to say, until NYT or the
State Department or something like that,
their implicit epistemology was, is a
reputable source saying it?
If so, then true. If not, then false.
Now,
this was always bizarre to me because as
a research scientist, you're used to
figure out if something is true on your
own using logic and reason. And
eventually I was able to figure out this
difference between pre-headline people
and post-headline people.
A pre-headline person, you have some
scientific finding and you are going to
publish it and you are actually the
upstream source of that finding. Like
the press release will be based on your
paper.
Right? Or conversely, you have some VC
investment round and you know something
is true
before the world knows it's true.
So, you're actually upstream. It's like
a miner. You're mining truth before it's
being sold at the market.
However, you realize that actually the
guy who's a post-headline person has
some wisdom all his own because he
implicitly, I'm not saying they're doing
this explicitly, they kind of know that
you can only be a pre-headline person in
so many areas.
Right. Like you can't be an expert on
Turkish and Japanese and I don't know
Brazilian iron ore and so and so forth.
Much of what you're sensing is going to
be essentially on some web three of
trust, which is based on some
information supply chain, right?
Anyway, it was through thinking through
things like this and how we would build
a higher standard of truth Mhm. that got
me to where we were. Let me pause there.
Interesting.
Um yeah, I guess you've been thinking
about this for a really long time. And
then I think we've been thinking about
this for honestly maybe the past three
to six months as we saw the AI problem
get worse and worse. And there's this
interesting asymmetry. I mean, our team
is based in our software. There's so
many smart people working on
accelerating all this AI stuff, which is
really good. There's obviously
incredible positive externalities.
But I think if there's a techno
AI if there's a technology that's
genuinely so powerful, obviously it's
going to have negative externalities.
And I think there's very few people
focused on combating these negative
externalities.
And I think in this domain with the
pictures and images and fake audio and
you know,
the that poses real problems. And I do
think this is an area where the
combination of cryptographic hardware,
cryptographic software, chain of trust,
custody,
ledger of record, provable technology
broadly as a category can actually like
help some solve those negative
externalities.
Um
Amazing. Yeah, that's how I got to it.
But you got to it much earlier than all
of us, which is like kind of your
specialty, which is which is very cool.
Well, thank you. And but I but I
appreciate you also grinding through all
the details to actually build the SDK
and so on because obviously that's
non-trivial. Um so, let's talk more
about that. Uh and um
Uma, thank you for coming on Nerdy
Sidebar cast.
Thank you for having me.